<inm:Recordset xmlns:inm="inm">
    <inm:Record setEntry="2474">
<inm:recordid>4708</inm:recordid>
<inm:countrycode />
<inm:repositorycode />
<inm:unitcode />
<inm:repository>Rush University Medical Center Archives</inm:repository>
<inm:accession>Acc. 2006-11, 2007-007 and 2007-016</inm:accession>
<inm:unittitle>John Edward Schwendener Papers, 1895-1928</inm:unittitle>
<inm:paralleltitle />
<inm:othertitle />
<inm:gmd>manuscript</inm:gmd>
<inm:responsibility>Schwendener, John E., (1876-1928)</inm:responsibility>
<inm:distribution />
<inm:datecreate />
<inm:startdate>1895</inm:startdate>
<inm:enddate>1928</inm:enddate>
<inm:level />
<inm:extent>Items:  About 19 items
Linear feet:  0.25</inm:extent>
<inm:titlesource />
<inm:adminbiohist>1876:  John E. Schwendener was born in Keewaskum, Wisc., and grew up in Milwaukee, Wisc.

1895-1898:  Schwendener and his football teammates from East Side High  School in Milwaukee competed in the city championships.  He was also on the  track team and held his high school’s record for throwing a baseball.    After high school, Schwendener served as Athletic Director of Wayland  Academy in Waukesha, Wisc., and Athletic Coach at Carroll College in Milwaukee.    1898-1902:  When he moved to Chicago to attend Rush Medical College, Schwendener took advantage of Rush’s rapidly expanding athletics association. He joined the football and baseball teams and the newly established basketball team.   1902:  After graduating from Rush in 1902, Schwendener accepted an internship under  Dr. Nicholas Senn, professor of surgery at Rush.   1904:  Married Mary B. Conreliussen of Story City, Iowa.  1905:  Moved to Bryant, S.D.      1917-1919:  During World War I, he enlisted in the Medical Corps and  served as Captain at Camp Dodge near Des Moines, Iowa.  1920s:  Schwendener was very involved in serving his community as  shown by his following accomplishments: - County coroner until his death  - Member of the local Board of Health and the school board - Surgeon for the Milwaukee Railroad - President of the Merchants State Bank - Vice-President of the Bryant State Bank.   - Mason, Shriner, and member of the Order of the Eastern Star,  - Founder of his local American Legion Post.    1928:  Dr. Schwendener died soon after suffering a paralytic stroke while attending to a  house call.  He was 51 years old.

Most of this information was culled from John E. Schwendener’s obituary in Series 1.
</inm:adminbiohist>
<inm:custodhist />
<inm:acqinfo>Received from Mary Harding of Bemdji, Minn., in February 2007 (Acc. 2006-11, 2007-007 and 2007-016).</inm:acqinfo>
<inm:scopecontent>Rush Medical College student and physician John E. Schwendener was born in Keewaskum, Wisc., and grew up in Milwaukee, Wisc., 1876.  In high school, Schwendener already showed a predilection toward athletics, competing on his school’s track and football teams.  He moved to Chicago, Ill., to attend Rush Medical College in 1898, graduating in 1902.  While at Rush, he participated on the baseball, football, and basketball teams.  After graduating, Schwendener accepted an internship under  Dr. Nicholas Senn, professor of surgery at Rush.  Schwendener eventually moved to Bryant, S.D., where he was very involved in his community, serving as physician, county coroner, a member of the Board of Health and School Board and other various positions.  In 1928, he died soon after suffering a paralytic stroke while attending to a house call.  The John E. Schwendener Papers include biographical information, pictures, and a Rush Medical College baseball jersey, 1900.  Pictures include team portraits and other pictures of Schwendener and his high school and Rush Medical College sports teams.  Other pictures include non-sports related pictures, such as Schwendener as a student at Rush and pictures from his life in Bryant, S. D.</inm:scopecontent>
<inm:accruals />
<inm:arrangement />
<inm:access>Baseball jersey may not be handled by researchers.</inm:access>
<inm:reproduction>Copyright is retained by the authors of the items in these papers, or their descendants, as stipulated by United States copyright law.</inm:reproduction>
<inm:language>English</inm:language>
<inm:physcharacteristic />
<inm:findaid>Series 1. Biographical Information, 1902 and 1928

1 item
Scope Content: Biographical information includes John Schwendener’s diploma from Rush Medical College, 1902, and an obituary from a South Dakota newspaper, 1928.

[In Oversized Papers Folder 1 (OP-4708-1)]  Rush Medical College diploma, 18 June 1902
Box 1:  John E. Schwendener obituary, 1928.

Series 2. Pictures, 1895-1918 and undated

17 items
Scope Content:  Pictures include team portraits and other pictures of Schwendener and his high school and Rush Medical College sports teams.  In high school, Schwendener was part of the track and football teams.  At Rush, Schwendener was a member of the baseball, football, and basketball teams.  Other pictures include non-sports related pictures, such as Schwendener as a student at Rush and pictures from his life in Bryant, S. D.

Subseries 2.1.  Sports Teams Pictures, 1895-1901 and undated

11 items
Arrangement:  High school sports pictures, followed by Rush Medical College sports teams alphabetically by sport.
Scope Content:  John Schwendener was an athlete in high school and college.  In high school, he was a member of the football and track teams.  At Rush Medical College, Schwendener was a member of the baseball, basketball, and football teams.  Schwendener played the center field position on the baseball team and right half back (now known as running back) on the football team.  Little is known about Rush’s short-lived basketball team, and the 1899 basketball team portrait is one of the only known photographs of the team.

High School Sports:

Box 1:  High School Football, Schwendener with two teammates, [1895?]
[In Oversized Pictures Folder 1 (OPP-4708-1)]  High School Football, Schwendener in posed action shot with teammates, [1895?]
[In Oversized Pictures Folder 2 (OPP-4708-2)]  High School Track Team, undated

Rush Medical College Baseball:

[In Oversized Pictures Folder 3 (OPP-4708-3)]  Rush Medical College Baseball Team, Schwendener is seated on left in middle row, 1900

Rush Medical College Basketball:

[Oversized Pictures Folder 4 (OPP-4708-4)]  Rush Medical College Basketball Team, Schwendener, sporting a moustache, seated on the left, 1899

Rush Medical College Football:

Box 1:  Rush Medical College Football Team, includes names, [Front row: Schwendener, Bomgardner, Lamping; second row: Foley, Eignus, Walter B. Cory (Captain), Freeman, Redner; third row: Tobin, Farr, Moore, Lamberton, Stinson, Steuhaur; back row: McKirahan, McBride, and Grasse.] 1898
Box 1:  Rush Medical College Football Team, clipping with names, [Back row: Cragin, Graffe, Eignus, Shraeder, Moore, Freeman, Brown; second row from back: Gaumer, Farr (captain), Pierson; second row: Keenan, Bland, Nicholson, Gardner, Rider; front row: Schwendener, McKirahan, Tobin, Lamping; first row, reclined: “Chimmie” (mascot)] 1899
Box 1:  Rush Medical College Football, Schwendener with three teammates, [Schwendener, Tobin, Lamping, and McKirahan]  [1899?]
Rush Medical College Football Team, 1900
Box 1:  Rush Medical College Football, Schwendener with three teammates, [Schwendener, McKirahan, Toben, Lamping] 1900
[Oversized Pictures Folder 5 (OPP-4708-5)]  Rush Medical College Football Team, [Schwendener served as captain of team during his final year as a student at Rush. As captain, he had the honor of posing with a football. The football in this portrait displays the team’s winning score against “P &amp; S” the College of Physicians and Surgeons, Rush’s fiercest rivals.] 1901

Subseries 2.2.  Other Pictures, 1899-1918 and undated

6 items
Arrangement:  Chronological
Scope Content:  Other pictures include pictures not related to sports.

Box 1:  Schwendener and two classmates posing with cadaver at Rush Medical College, [1899?]
[In Oversized Pictures Folder 6 (OPP-4708-6)]  Dr. Nicholas Senn’s Clinic, Schwendener in front row, 1902
Box 1:  Schwendener Family Portrait with wife Mary and daughter Dorothy, [1910?]
Box 1:  Schwendener in World War I uniform, [1918?]
Box 1:  Dr. John Schwendener and Dr. Al Guse, DDS, at hunting shack on Lake Poinsett, S. D., undated
Box 1:  Schwendener Residence, Bryant, S.D., undated

Series 3. Artifacts, 1900

1 item
Use Restriction:  Wool baseball jersey must be handled carefully, with gloves.
Scope Content: Artifacts include John Schwendener’s Rush Medical College baseball jersey, 1900.  This is the same jersey worn in the Rush Medical College baseball team portrait, 1900.  The short-sleeved, buttoned jersey is made of gray wool with dark red felt lettering, “RUSH.”

Textile cabinet?:  Schwendener’s wool Rush Medical College Baseball Jersey, 1900
</inm:findaid>
<inm:originals />
<inm:copies />
<inm:image />
<inm:relatedmaterial>Rush Medical College I Records, #4707</inm:relatedmaterial>
<inm:separatedmaterial>Pictures and artifact</inm:separatedmaterial>
<inm:bibliography />
<inm:generalnote>Processed by:  Nathalie Wheaton (September 2007)</inm:generalnote>
<inm:standardnumber />
<inm:location />
<inm:containercode />
<inm:archivistnote>The papers of Rush Medical College student and physician John E. Schwendener include biographical information, pictures, and a Rush Medical College baseball jersey, 1900.  Biographical information includes John Schwendener’s diploma from Rush Medical College, 1902, and an obituary from a South Dakota newspaper, 1928.  Pictures include team portraits and other pictures of Schwendener and his high school and Rush Medical College sports teams.  In high school, Schwendener was part of the track and football teams.  At Rush, Schwendener was a member of the baseball, football, and basketball teams.  Other pictures include non-sports related pictures, such as Schwendener as a student at Rush and pictures from his life in Bryant, S. D.  Also included is Schwendener’s 1900 Rush Medical College baseball jersey.

ARRANGEMENT OF SERIES:

1. Biographical information, 1902 and 1928
2. Pictures, 1895-1918 and undated
2.1.  Sports Teams Pictures, 1895-1901 and undated
2.2.  Other Pictures, 1899-1918 and undated
3. Artifacts, 1900</inm:archivistnote>
<inm:citation>[Identification of item], in the John E. Schwendener Papers, Rush University Medical Center Archives.
</inm:citation>
<inm:rules />
<inm:subjects>Baseball—Chicago, Ill.
Basketball—Chicago, Ill.
College sports—Chicago, Ill.
Football—Chicago, Ill.
Chicago, Ill.
Rush Medical College
Rush Medical College—Baseball History
Rush Medical College—Basketball History
Rush Medical College—Football History
Rush Medical College (1837-1942)—Sports
Rush Medical College (1837-1942)—History
Rush University Medical Center—History, 19th century
Rush University Medical Center—History, 20th century
Schwendener, John E., 1876-1928
Senn, Nicholas, 1844-1908
University of Chicago—Sports History
</inm:subjects>
<inm:namessubjects />
<inm:series />
<inm:file />
<inm:folder />
<inm:recordtype />
</inm:Record>
</inm:Recordset>